<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Random Ramble with Drift - Articles</title>
    <description>Demography, Data Science, and other Deliberations</description>
    <link>
    http://localhost:4000</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Explicit Link Between GMRF to GF (Part 2)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a continuation of the write up describing the main results of a foundational paper in geostatistics &amp;ldquo;An explicit link between Gaussian fields and Gaussian Markov random fields: the stochastic partial differential equation approach&amp;rdquo; by Lindgren, Rue, and Lindstrom. It also demos how to make use the findings in the paper in R and vizualize the results. See the first post &lt;a href=&quot;https://nmmarquez.github.io/explicit-link-between-gmrf-gf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/explicit-link-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/explicit-link-2</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Explicit Link Between GMRF to GF (Part 1)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;This is largely a write up describing the main results of a foundational paper in geostatistics &amp;ldquo;An explicit link between Gaussian fields and Gaussian Markov random fields: the stochastic partial differential equation approach&amp;rdquo; by Lindgren, Rue, and Lindstrom. It also demos how to make use the findings in the paper in R and vizualize the results. This is especially applicable for cases when you have spatial point data that is unevenly spaced.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/explicit-link-between-gmrf-gf</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/explicit-link-between-gmrf-gf</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Confidence Intervals &amp; Bias</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In order to get a good idea of the underlying theory of frequentist confidence intervals and how model assumptions could potentially bias our results we examine a set of simulations below to test the estimation of a single known parameter, in the code referred to as &lt;code&gt;trueValue&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/confidence-intervals-bias</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/confidence-intervals-bias</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Using ACS Data Directly From R</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;This post goes over how to download and use Census and ACS data from within R using the &lt;code&gt;tidycensus&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;acs&lt;/code&gt; packages. When possible I would suggest using the &lt;code&gt;tidycensus&lt;/code&gt; package as the functions are much easier to work with and provide a cleaner output. The &lt;code&gt;tidycensus&lt;/code&gt; package, unfortunately, does not cover the entirity of the census geographies and that is when we must use the &lt;code&gt;acs&lt;/code&gt; package. They both access the same data so reults should not differ if you decide to use one package over another.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/acs-demo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/acs-demo</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>R Shiny Server</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up your own shiny server can be helpful to host a few small projects that you want to share with a few collaborators. I am going to go through the setup of starting a server, like through Amazon EWS or Digital Ocean, and through the necessary steps that you will need to take in order to be able to get access to that server securely. These instructions are specific to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ubuntu&lt;/code&gt; 16.04 but shouldn’t change that much across different versions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 02:18:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/r-shiny-server</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/r-shiny-server</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Gibbs and MH Mix</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;For any one who writes anything data science related there comes a time when they discover the &lt;del&gt;pain&lt;/del&gt; joy of writing there own MCMC sampler from scratch and the inevitable need to tell everyone about it. For me, now is that time and after getting my butt kicked in my stochastic modeling class I fell like I need to at least write about the one thing that I did want to take away from the class and feel like I got a decent handle on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 02:18:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/the-gibbs-and-MH-Mix</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/the-gibbs-and-MH-Mix</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Rejection Sampling</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Rejection sampling allows us to sample from some target distribution when we have a proposal distribution. The algorithm works by first drawing a random value, say \(u\), that is between zero and one from uniform (\(U(0,1)\)) distribution. Next a random value for \(x\) is drawn from the proposal distribution \(f(x)\). Finally there is an acceptance/rejection step that asks: if the probability \(u\) is less than the density of \(g(x)\) at \(x\) divided by the density of \(f(x)*p_A\) then we&amp;#39;ll accept \(x\) as having been drawn from \(g(x)\). If not well sample another value for \(x\) from \(f(x)\) and try again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 02:18:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/Rejection-Sampling</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Rejection-Sampling</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>NB1 and NB2 Dispersion</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The other day I started working with a colleague on propagating uncertainty for
a negative binomial generalized linear model. To my surprise I found that there
was a couple of different ways to define the probability distribution that led
to more than a bit of confusion on my end, but got me messing around with how
you could simulate over-dispersed count data in a couple of ways. It also got me
working with TMB again and the woes of dealing with nonlinear optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 02:50:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/nb1-nb2-uncertainty</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/nb1-nb2-uncertainty</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Simulating Spatially Correlated Data</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I ran into a problem where I needed to create some spatially correlated data for a project and I
realized that I didn’t know the first thing about how to go about doing it. I was lucky to find that the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1601.01180&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that I was trying to replicate did a great job of detailing their methods in
such a way that I was able to create some spatial data of my own. The idea is that you need to create a covariance
matrix of the relationships of your data to pull form a multivariate random normal distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 14:47:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/simulating-spatial-data</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/simulating-spatial-data</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Latex with Jekyll</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I am trying out a new layout that will hopefully let me do inline latex like so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt; as well as its own thing like&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2016 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/latex-with-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/latex-with-jekyll</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Hello Worlds</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up a blog so I have a place to post my ideas and work that I manage to do outside of work and school (ha!).
Hoping this is the beginning of something long and beautiful so here goes nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2016 03:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:4000/hello-worlds</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/hello-worlds</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
